Whiting Griswold Correspondence
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Whiting Griswold Correspondence 1843-1874
MSS58131
Griswold, Whiting, 1814-1874
210 items
1 container
.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer and politician. Letters to Griswold from various prominent figures relating to such topics as the Whig, Free Soil, and American parties, the Democratic Party, his legal practice, Massachusetts politics, patronage, the Hoosac Tunnel, the Kansas-Nebraska Act, the Civil War, and the 1853 Massachusetts Constitutional Convention.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Banks, Nathaniel Prentiss, 1816-1894--Correspondence.; Boutwell, George S. (George Sewall), 1818-1905--Correspondence.; Butler, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1818-1893--Correspondence.; Cushing, Caleb, 1800-1879--Correspondence.; Griswold, Whiting, 1814-1874.; Hallett, Benjamin Franklin, 1797-1862--Correspondence.; Hoar, George Frisbie, 1826-1904--Correspondence.; Loring, George B. (George Bailey), 1817-1891--Correspondence.; Phillips, Wendell, 1811-1884--Correspondence.; Sumner, Charles, 1811-1874--Correspondence.; Whitney, James Lyman, 1835-1910--Correspondence.; Wilson, Henry, 1812-1875--Correspondence.
Organizations
American Party.; Democratic Party (U.S.); Free Soil Party (U.S.); Massachusetts. Constitutional Convention (1853); United States. Kansas-Nebraska Act.; Whig Party (U.S.)
Subjects
Constitutional conventions--Massachusetts.; Patronage, Political.; Political parties--United States.; Practice of law--Massachusetts.; Tunnels--Massachusetts.
Places
Hoosac Tunnel (Mass.); Massachusetts--Politics and government.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--Politics and government--19th century.
Titles
Whiting Griswold papers
Occupations
Lawyers.; Politicians.
Provenance
The correspondence of Whiting Griswold, lawyer and politician, was purchased by the Library of Congress in 1978.
Access and Restrictions
The correspondence of Whiting Griswold is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1814, Nov. 12 Born, Buckland, Mass.
1838 Graduated, Amherst College, Amherst, Mass.
1842 Became member of the bar, Franklin County, Mass.
1848 1850 Member, Massachusetts state legislature
1851 1852 Senator, Massachusetts state legislature
1853 Member, Massachusetts state constitutional convention
1864 Presidential elector for Abraham Lincoln from Massachusetts
1874, Oct. 28 Died, Greenfield, Mass.
Scope and Content Note
The correspondence of Whiting Griswold (1814-1874) consists of letters addressed to him over the period 1843-1874. As a prominent lawyer in western Massachusetts and an active politician, Griswold’s advice and counsel were sought by prominent figures from all over the state. This correspondence bulks largest for the 1850s and 1860s and is concerned chiefly with politics on the local, state, and national levels. The disruption of parties in the 1850s is well documented, particularly with regard to the decline of the Whigs and the rise of the Free Soil and American (or Know Nothing) parties, as viewed from the vantage point of the Democratic Party. Other subjects include legal questions, patronage, the Hoosac Tunnel in Massachusetts, the Kansas-Nebraska Bill, the Civil War, and the Massachusetts Constitutional Convention of 1853. Among the principal correspondents are Nathaniel Prentiss Banks, George S. Boutwell, Benjamin F. Butler, Caleb Cushing, Benjamin Franklin Hallett (1797-1862), George Frisbie Hoar, George B. Loring, Wendell Phillips, Charles Sumner, James Lyman Whitney, and Henry Wilson.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is organized alphabetically by name of correspondent.
Container List
- Adams, Charles Francis, 1869 (Box 1)
- Adams, Isaac, 1860 (Box 1)
- Allen, Charles, 1865-1873 (Box 1)
- Allen, Elisha Hunt, 1865-1873 (Box 1)
- Andrew, John A., 1862-1863 (Box 1)
- Andrew, John F., 1886 (Box 1)
- Banks, Nathaniel Prentiss, 1851-1867 (Box 1)
- Boutwell, George S., 1848-1874 (Box 1)
- Butler, Benjamin F., 1852-1874 (Box 1)
- Chapin, Chester W., 1850 (Box 1)
- Choate, Rufus, 1857 (Box 1)
- Coffin, Sirson P., 1849-1855 (Box 1)
- Crocker, Alvah, 1862-1866 (Box 1)
- Curtis, Benjamin R., 1873 (Box 1)
- Cushing, Caleb, 1848-1854 (Box 1)
- Cushman, Henry W., 1845-1853 (Box 1)
- Dawes, Henry L., 1861-1863 (Box 1)
- Gray, Horace, 1855 (Box 1)
- Hale, Nathan (Box 1)
- Hallett, Benjamin F., 1843-1862 (Box 1)
- Harris, Daniel L., 1862 (Box 1)
- Hillard, George S., 1852-1873 (Box 1)
- Hoar, Ebenezer R., 1871-1873 (Box 1)
- Hoar, George Frisbie., 1863-1869 (Box 1)
- Huntington, Frederick D., 1857 (Box 1)
- Jewell, Harvey, 1869 (Box 1)
- Lewis, Dioclesian, 1862 (Box 1)
- Lord, Otis P., 1857-1873 (Box 1)
- Loring, George B., 1850-1864 (Box 1)
- Maynard, Horace, 1860 (Box 1)
- Phillips, Wendell, 1869 (Box 1)
- Summer, Charles, 1865-1869 (Box 1)
- Tyler, William S., 1850-1851 (Box 1)
- Walker, Amasa, 1864 (Box 1)
- Washburn, Emory, 1869-1873 (Box 1)
- Whitney, James Lyman, 1841-1857 (Box 1)
- Wilder, Marshall P., 1873 (Box 1)
- Wilson, Henry, 1853-1867 (Box 1)
- Woodbury, Levi, 1845 (Box 1)